Guide to the Richard Erdoes Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Audio Recordings, 1964-1996; Series V; 30.86; (74 boxes)
  - Leonard Crow Dog
    - Interviews
      - Yellow Thunder case at Gordon, Nebraska and Penitentiary Indian Inmates / Peyote Songs, 1972 May 22; 1 (Box 106, Item barcode 39002091247818)
        Summary: Leonard Crow Dog discusses the burial of Raymond Yellow Thunder, the National First Annual Convention in Minneapolis (?), the American Indian Movement, and religion. Crow Dog also speaks about Stillwater, Minnesota's state prision, use of the peace pipe, civil rights, and a court case focusing on peyote use. There is further discussion of religion and drugs, as well as a song, accompanied by drums.
      - Leonard talks about AIM (audiotape reel), 1972 May 22; 1 (Box 107, Item barcode 39002091247826)
        Container Annotated: "Side One about AIM Movement General Philosophy. Second Side: Yellow Thunder case at Gordon, Nebraska. L. Crow Dog, Transcription pp. 1-20."
      - Leonard Crow Dog "Legends" (audiotape reel), 1972 May 23; 1 (Box 107, Item barcode 39002091247834)
        Summary: Leonard Crow Dog tells legends about the sun and earth.
      - "Peyote", Leonard Crow Dog (audiotape reel), 1972 May 23; 1 (Box 107, Item barcode 39002091247842)
        Summary: Singing and drumming. First song: "I made that song after midnight, after drinking water, withpthe Peyote power in [mt]." Annotation reads: (My dad made this song.)
      - Rattlesnake legend, Cottonwood legend, Thunderbirds, [C]anon day Heyoka, Drtams, Wayinya, Sacred Things, Wigmuge, heyoka, Medicine, 1972[?] May 26; 1 (Box 107, Item barcode 39002091247859)
        Running time: 29 minutes
        Speakers: Leonard Crow Dog recites sayings, and discusses symbols and ceremonies
      - Leonard Crow Dog, "Peyote Songs of Leonard and Paul Armstrong" (audiotape reel), 1972 May [23?]; 1 (Box 107, Item barcode 39002091247867)
        Running time: 1 hour, 20 minutes
        Summary: Leonard Crow Dog sings, accompanied by drum and other instruments. He discusses visiting a meeting, the Native American Church, and compares the open quality of Native American religious ceremonies to other reglious traditions. Crow Dog also discusses peace pipes.
      - Leonard Crow Dog, "Legends" / "The Coming of Wasicun" (audiotape reel), 1972 May 29-30; 1 (Box 107, Item barcode 39002091247875)
        Summary: Leonard Crow Dog discusses peyote experiences, songs, rituals, and the construction of drums. He also discusses symbols and traditions of the Native American Church, including the "Morning Star Baptism," before telling legends.
      - Leonard Crow Dog, "Sioux Legends", story of Iyan, story of Wasicun (audiotape reel), 1972 May 30; 1 (Box 107, Item barcode 39002091247883)
        Running time: 49 minutes
        Summary: Leonard Crow Dog tells the legend of the first human, of the creation of animals and trees, and other legends.
      - Leonard Crow Dog, "Legends" (audiotape reel), 1972 May; 1 (Box 108, Item barcode 39002091247891)
        Running time: 51 minutes
        Summary: Leonard Crow Dog tells a number of legends, including one about four hunters and sacred buffalo, and one about a boy and his grandmother
      - Crow Dog & Wallace Black Elk in Wounded Knee, on the death of Frank Clearwater (audiocassette), 1973 April 5; 1 (Box 108, Item barcode 39002091247909)
        Running time: 25 minutes
        Summary: Leonard Crow Dog speaks about Wounded Knee, including Frank Clearwater's death and burial. Crow Dog and Black Elk speak in Lakota. Black Elk speaks about Frank Clearwater, the American Indian Movement, and the Bureau of Indian Affairs. An unidentified woman recounts the situation at Wounded Knee
      - Crow Dog, WBAI, NY (1 of 2 audiocassettes), 1973 July 12; 1 (Box 108, Item barcode 39002091247917)
        Running time: 1 hour, 2 minutes
        Summary: Leonard Crow Dog discusses the American Indian Movement and sings songs. He discusses Wounded Knee and other American Indian historical, political and social issues, including the Trail of Broken Treaties, the impact of alcohol, the Indian Reorganization Act, and Dick Wilson
      - Crow Dog, WBAI, NY (2 of 2 audiocassettes), 1973 July 12; 1 (Box 108, Item barcode 39002091247925)
      - Crow Dog, "BIA + Boyhood" / "Boyhood + Medicine", WBAI (audiocassette), 1973 November 17; 1 (Box 108, Item barcode 39002091247933)
        Running time: 1 hour, 33 minutes
        Summary: Leonard Crow Dog discusses his life and childhood, baseball, medicine, the American Indian Movement, and land issues
      - Crow Dog on AIM (Dad Repro) (audiocassette), 1973 November 22; 1 (Box 108, Item barcode 39002091247941)
        Running time: 8 minutes
        Summary: Richard Erdoes and Leonard Crow Dog record a statement for radio broadcast. An unidentified woman reads a 1973 November 22 American Indian Movement statement about a boycott of alcohol and drugs on reservations across the United States
        First and last minute of recording is silent. Recording is inaudible in places because of technical difficulties with original recording equipment.
      - Matthew King, Ellen Moves Camp, Leonard Crow Dog, taped at Wounded Knee (audiocassette), 1973; 1 (Box 108, Item barcode 39002091247958)
        Summary: A man, likely Matthew King, is interviewed by an unidentified woman. King talks about white people, treaties, and religion. At 13:02, Ellen Crow Dog talks about the American Indian Movement and political affairs on Pine Ridge Reservation. At 15:20, Leonard Crow Dog talks about the American Indian Movement, his involvement in AIM, Wounded Knee, and the American Indian civil rights movement. An unidentified man, possibly a reporter, questions Crow Dog
        Recording is spliced together and there are drop-outs and silences throughout
      - "Peyote Songs", Charlie Kills Enemy and Leonard Crow Dog / "Sioux Lesson" (audiotape reel), [1974?] May 10; 1 (Box 109, Item barcode 39002091247966)
        Summary: Peyote song by Charlie Kills Enemy and Leonard Crow Dog and a Lakota Sioux translation lesson
      - Leonard Crow Dog at Richards (audiocassette), 1974 November 18; 1 (Box 109, Item barcode 39002091247974)
        Summary: Singing and drumming
      - "Leonard: His Life" (audiocassette), 1975 October 27; 1 (Box 109, Item barcode 39002091247982)
        Running time: 28 minutes
        Summary: Leonard Crow Dog talks about his life (rights, advice to family), sings, and recounts memories of his father's birthday
      - Leonard Crow Dog, "Good Peyote Song" (audiocassette), 1976 March 30; 1 (Box 109, Item barcode 39002091247990)
        Running time: 3 minutes
      - Crow Dog, "Medicine" (audiocassette), 1976 April 3; 1 (Box 109, Item barcode 39002091248006)
        Running time: 1 hour, 27 minutes
        Summary: Leonard Crow Dog is interviewed by Richard Erdoes about his treatment in prison, and his trial. Crow Dog also interviews Wallace Black Elk. Annotation on audiocassette reads "very good!"
      - Leonard Crow Dog, "Talk about Prison" (audiocassette), 1977 April 12-14; 1 (Box 109, Item barcode 39002091248014)
        Running time: 1 hour 28 minutes
        Speakers: Leonard Crow Dog
        Summary: Leonard Crow Dog discusses spirituality, struggles, multiple prison transfers, visions, psychological assessment, "lifers", maximum security, struggles of other prisoners, mail, parole boards, support, friends in penitentiary, mentality in prison. Other topics include: "hacks", Siouan language abilities, homosexuality, the American Indian Religious Freedom Act, religion in prison, spirituality, and Christianity
        Recording repeatedly cuts out for about five seconds between 12.00 and 16.00 minutes
      - Crow Dog, [Washington] DC, audiocassette, 1977 April 25; 1 (Box 110, Item barcode 39002091248022)
        Running time: 57 minutes
        Summary: Leonard Crow Dog, likely talking at a media event, speaks about the treatment and future of Indians in the United States, and about the American Indian Movement. Erdoes and Crow Dog interview Tony Strong, assistant to Senator James Abourezk, about treaty rights, laws, politics, and the Committee on Indian Affairs
      - "Peyote ceremony", Leonard Crow Dog, Ironshell, Rocky Dunes, Lefthand Bull, Wayne Scout, Jerry Roy, 1977 August; 1 (Box 110, Item barcode 39002091248030)
        Running time: 48 minutes. 7.5 ips, monophonic, 2 half tracks
        Recording is muffled. Sound stops at approx. 32 minutes
      - Leonard Crow Dog "Sundance", 2 peyote songs (audiocassette), 1981 March 21; 1 (Box 110, Item barcode 39002091248048)
        Running time: 7 minutes
        Summary: Leonard Crow Dog talks about spiritual experiences and war
      - Leonard Crow Dog, "Soul Keeping" / "Sundance" (audiocassette), 1981 March 21; 1 (Box 110, Item barcode 39002091248055)
        Running time: 1 hour 32 minutes
        Summary: Leonard Crow Dog tells stories related to spiritual matters, Lakota traditions, and his family. He discusses his life, family traditions, and the Sun Dance
      - Leonard, "Creation", to 10.20 AM (audiocassette), 1981 March 18; 1 (Box 110, Item barcode 39002091248063)
        Running time: 1 hour, 32 minutes
        Summary: Leonard Crow Dog discusses creation and the caretaker role of humans. Henry Crow Dog discusses school, gasoline and cars, death, and politics
        Recording is very quiet
      - Leonard Crow Dog on Buffalo Pipe, His Youth; Sundance Yuwipi (audiotape reel), 1981 March; 1 (Box 111, Item barcode 39002091248071)
        Running time: 1 hour, 12 minutes
        Summary: Leonard Crow Dog discusses the Sun Dance, visions, the Yuwipi Ceremony, the Spider Cermeony, and the origins of the Lakota people and their history. Crow Dog also speaks about the sacred White Buffalo Calf Pipe, and his youth
      - Leonard Family History (audiocassette), 1981; 1 (Box 111, Item barcode 39002091248089)
        Running time: 35 minutes
        Summary: Leonard Crow Dog discusses his grandfathers, Lakota clans, and the location of his family, before a providing a series of Lakota words with English translation
        Recording cuts to silence at approximately 29 minutes
      - Leonard Crow Dog (audiocassette), 1983 September 8; 1 (Box 111, Item barcode 39002091248097)
        Running time: 1 hour, 21 minutes
        Speaker: Leonard Crow Dog speaks about spriritual stones and traditions
      - Crow Dog on Ghost Dance (audiocassette), March 21 (Box 111, Item barcode 39002091248105)
        Summary: Leonard Crow Dog, at a meeting at Wounded Knee, discusses the Ghost Dance and the Sun Dance the night before it was held.
      - "Crowdog / Wallace Black Elk, 1A, Westport rally (audiocassette), April 8-9; 1 (Box 111, Item barcode 39002091248113)
        Running time: 1 hour, 37 min
        Summary: Leonard Crow Dog and Wallace Black Elk discuss the definition of "Indian," their creation beliefs, war, and conflict. They also discuss the Thunderbird American Indian Dancers. Crow Dog discusses the death, autopsy, and burial of Pedro Bissonette, political elections and tribal leadership, the 1868 Fort Laramie Treaty, and warrants on the Rosebud Reservation. Crow Dog and Black Elk also discuss spiritual matters, speaking about a sacred gourd, the Sacred Pipe, creation, children, and language education, as well as UFOs. Black Elk discusses his commitment to Lakota burial and marriage traditions
      - Leonard Crow Dog talks about family, old times (audiotape reel), undated; 1 (Box 112, Item barcode 39002091248121)
        Running time: 1 hour, 6 minutes
        Summary: Leonard Crow Dog discusses the Ghost Dance and plans for a Ghost Dance revival, other ceremonies, and the death of grandfather John Crow Dog. He also discusses the construction of houses and churches, and speaks about the spiritual power of rocks.
      - L. Crow Dog, "Peyote Songs", Alex One Star (audiocassette), undated; 1 (Box 112, Item barcode 39002091248139)
        Running time: 24 minutes
        Summary: Leonard Crow Dog speaks about his spritual experiences
      - Leonard Crow Dog, Ann Arbor (audiocassette), undated; 1 (Box 112, Item barcode 39002091248147)
        Running time: 1 hour, 1 minute
        Summary: Leonard Crow Dog discusses his ancestors and ancestral traditions
      - "At Crow Dog's", Diane Erdoes (audiocassette), undated; 1 (Box 112, Item barcode 39002091248154)
        Summary: Leonard Crow Dog, Diane Erdoes, and Richard Erdoes speak about the demands of civil rights treaties, the Wounded Knee memorial, and religion
      - Crow Dog interview by Erdoes (audiocassette), undated; 1 (Box 112, Item barcode 39002091248162)
        Running time: 1 hour, 15 minutes
        Summary: Leonard Crow Dog discusses ceremonies, peyote, Little Big Horn, the Ghost Dance, Red Cloud, Dick Wilson (Oglala tribal chairman, 1972-1976), and his father. Last half hour is mixture of choral and instrumental European music, with English voice-over
        Recording is interrupted by accordian music
      - Leonard Crow Dog, "Medicine Talk" (audiocassette), undated; 1 (Box 112, Item barcode 39002091248170)
        Running time: 58 minutes
        Summary: Leonard Crow Dog talks about the American Indian Movement, the Native American Church, the Sun Dance, and spiritual matters
      - Crow Dog, "Medicine Talk", AIM (audiocassette), undated; 1 (Box 113, Item barcode 39002091248634)
        Running time: 59 minutes
        Duplicate of previous recording
      - "Sioux Dictionary" (audiotape reel), undated; 1 (Box 113, Item barcode 39002091248642)
        Summary: Leonard Crow Dog translates Sioux words and phrases
      - Leonard Crow Dog, "Radio Interview" (audiocassette), undated; 1 (Box 113, Item barcode 39002091248659)
        Summary: "Speak Out" radio program. Interview with David Red Bird, Leonard Crow Dog, and Owen Thundertrail. Topics include AIM, Wounded Knee, false association of the American Indian civil rights movement with communism, militancy, culture clash, ethnocide, racism, terrorism, Pedro Bissonette's death, the Bureau of Indian Affairs, and the American Indian National Bank
      - Leonard on Cankpe Opi (audiocassette), undated; 1 (Box 113, Item barcode 39002091248667)
        Running time: 1 hour, 3 minutes
        Summary: A woman, Winona, is interviewed by Erdoes and talks about her experiences at Wounded Knee. Recording includes Erdoes's interviews with Leonard Crow Dog, and possibly other unidentified men, about the occupation at Wounded Knee
        Multiple tracks. Third track is mostly silent and recorded at high speed
      - "Explanation of Native American Church" (audiotape reel), undated; 1 (Box 113, Item barcode 39002091248675)
        Running time: 17 minutes
        Summary: Singing, followed by Leonard Crow Dog giving a speech about the Native American Church, its ceremonies, and the use of peyote. Crow Dog's speech is followed by a similar speech by a Native Americn Church leader
      - Crow Dog (audiocassette), undated; 1 (Box 113, Item barcode 39002091248683)
        This audiocasette has not been reformatted.
    - Songs and Ceremonies
      Songs and Ceremonies consists of eleven recordings that Erdoes made of Leonard Crow Dog singing Native American Indian Church ceremonial and peyote songs. The earliest recording in the set is from 1968; the last dated recording is from 1983. The singing is often accompanied by drumming. On some recordings, a description of the song or an introduction has been recorded.
      - Crow Dog's "Peyote Songs" (audiotape reel), 1968 May 1; 1 (Box 114, Item barcode 39002091248691)
        Native American Indian Church Songs. Singing by Leonard Crow Dog and Charles Kills Enemy. Short speech by Leonard Crow. Sings with drum and rattle.
      - Sioux Prayer Yuwipi at Leonard's (Our First)" (audiotape reel), 1968; 1 (Box 114, Item barcode 39002091248709)
        Running time: 1 hour, 34 minutes
        Summary: Recording of Yuwipi ceremony
      - Leonard, "Peyote Songs" (audiotape reel), 1972 May 24; 1 (Box 114, Item barcode 39002091248717)
        Running time: 26 minutes
        Starts with "Peyote Songs", "Sacred Horse Legend", "Siyoko".
      - "Rosebud Powwow" / Leonard Crow Dog at Richard's, "Songs inside Wounded Knee"(audiocassette), 1974 November; 1 (Box 114, Item barcode 39002091248741)
        Summary: Powwow and honor songs introduced by Leonard Crow Dog
        First track is blank
      - Crow Dog, "Kangi Sunka", New York City, 1977 April 13 (Box 114, Item barcode 39002091248733)
        Running time: 41 minutes
      - Crow Dog, "Peyote Songs", Kangisunka, New York City (audiocassette), 1977 April 13; 1 (Box 114, Item barcode 39002091248725)
      - Leonard Crow Dog, Bill Hawn, Mary Ellen Crow Dog, "Peyote Songs", Chief honoring song (audiotape reel), 1983 September 14; 1 (Box 115, Item barcode 39002091248758)
        Original recording had drum distortion
      - Leonard: Nat. Am. Church (audiotape reel), undated; 1 (Box 115, Item barcode 39002091248766)
        Annotation reads: how to use the peyote (in Rosebud). I start out [with] 4 spoons, no gimmick, no drug.
      - Leonard Crow Dog, "Peyote Songs" (audiotape reel), undated; 1 (Box 115, Item barcode 39002091248774)
      - Short peyote song by Leonard (audiotape reel), undated; 1 (Box 115, Item barcode 39002091248782)
      - "Peyote 41", meeting Good One, duet singing (audiotape reel), undated; 1 (Box 115, Item barcode 39002091248808)
      - "1st Peyote", Leonard Crow Dog (audiotape reel), undated; 1 (Box 115, Item barcode 39002091248790)
        This audiotape reel includes: Coughing Than Duet, Drum Loud, Fa[?] [?]one Whistle, Singing in Background, Barney Iron Shell, George Gap, Ed Eagle Elk, Francis Masters, Charlie Little Eagle.
      - Crow Dog, "Peyote Singing" (audiocassette), undated; 1 (Box 116, Item barcode 39002091248816)
      - "Indian Wedding Ceremony" (audiotape reel), undated; 1 (Box 116, Item barcode 39002091248824)
        Summary: Includes interview about traditional ceremony, beliefs, and artifacts (drums, feathers, peyote), along with singing and drumming
        First 30 seconds of original recording were "blank at the head"
    - Speeches
      Speeches consists of five recordings of Crow Dog speaking publicly at various locations during the 1970s. His themes include religious freedom for American Indians, the federal government's treatment of American Indian nations, the American Indian Movement, the Native American Church, and his experience as a medicine man and spiritual leader.
      - Leonard Crow Dog, "Peyote 1A" (audiotape reel), 1970 October; 1 (Box 116, Item barcode 39002091248832)
        Summary: A speech by Crow Dog about fair treatment and peyote. Singing and drumming follow, with a discussion of peyote
        Recording is muffled at beginning
      - Crow Dog "Princeton" (audiocassette), 1973 November; 1 (Box 116, Item barcode 39002091248840)
        Running time: 2 hours, 2 minutes
        Summary: Leonard Crow Dog speaks about his birth and being a medicine man. Topics include fasting, the American Indian Movement, religion, Wounded Knee, Crow Dog's sacred eagle, piercing, peyote, the Bible, heaven, and blood quantum. Crow Dog also speaks about the "Christianization" and representation of American Indians, peace, his family, prayer, and sacred objects. Another man speaks further about Wounded Knee
      - Crow Dog rally, Westport, CT / Jim Post live (Audiocassette), 1976 April 8-9; 1 (Box 116, Item barcode 39002091248857)
        Running time: 40 minutes
        Summary: Recording of various excerpts, mainly recorded at rally. Includes speech by Richard Erdoes about Leonard Crow Dog's trial and imprisonment. Two tracks
      - Crow Dog rally, Westport (audiocassette), 1976 April 8-9; 1 (Box 116, Item barcode 39002091248865)
        Summary: Leonard Crow Dog speaks about the United States government's relationship with Native nations, about the Bureau of Indian Affairs, stereotypes, "going traditional" spiritual leadership, injustice, Black Elk, and Lakota prayer. Crow Dog also discusses the federal recognition process, his experience in a penetentiary, and spiritual leadership. Other topics include children, language, and political issues
        Recording ends abruptly
      - "Flag Raising 1", New Wilderness (audiotape reel), [1970s?]; 1 (Box 117, Item barcode 39002091248873)
        Summary: A man, likely Leonard Crow Dog, speaks about the American Indian Movement during a flag raising outside a courthouse. Oglala Sioux civil right leader Pedro Bissonette is mentioned, along with the 1974 Ghost Dance
  - Mary Brave Bird and Leonard Crow Dog
    This subseries is arranged chronologically. Undated recordings are listed after dated recordings.
    The Mary Brave Bird and Leonard Crow Dog subseries consists of seven recordings which Richard Erdoes made of the pair during their marriage. Dated recordings span from 1975 to 1980. Three of the recordings are joint interviews of Brave Bird and Crow Dog, addressing personal topics about their lives and their relationship, as well as broader social issues, such as the forced sterilization of American Indian women, birth control, gender, violence, and spirituality. The other four recordings are of Brave Bird and Crow Dog singing and drumming ceremonial songs, mainly related to the peyote sacrament.
    - Mary Ellen Crow Dog, Interview woman / Disc. Sterile Indian Women, 1975 October 25; 1 (Box 117, Item barcode 39002091248881)
      Summary: Mary Brave Bird and Leonard Crow Dog discuss forced sterilization, birth control, breast feeding, and action against the government
    - Leonard Crow Dog / Christine & Mary Crow Dog, The New Wilderness Foundation (audiocassette), 1977 April 12; 1 (Box 117, Item barcode 39002091248899)
      Summary: Recording of a song
      Left and right channels split onto separate tracks, stereo
    - "Leonard & Mary Crow Dog", New Wilderness Audiographics (audiocassette), 1977 [April 12]; 1 (Box 117, Item barcode 39002091248915)
      Left and right channels split onto separate tracks. Duplicate of previous recording
    - Leonard and Mary Crow Dog on prison / Leonard on peyote (audiocassette), 1977 April 19; 1 (Box 117, Item barcode 39002091248907)
      Running time: 1 hour, 29 minutes
      Summary: Mary Brave Bird discusses her life after the 1973 Wounded Knee occupation. Leonard Crow Dog discusses prison life and peyote
    - Leonard Crow Dog and Mary Crow Dog, "Peyote Songs", 1st session, The New Wilderness Foundation, 1977 April 22; 1 (Box 118, Item barcode 39002091248923)
      Running time: 50 minutes
      Summary: Peyote songs, singing and drumming
    - Mary and Leonard on Sundance (audiocassette), 1980 February 25; 1 (Box 118, Item barcode 39002091248931)
      Summary: Mary Brave Bird and Leonard Crow Dog discuss dancing and body piercing, particularly among women. Crow Dog also talks about the buffalo calf pipe, and Mary's family. Mary talks about meeting and then living with Leonard, her first ceremonies, peyote, Leonard and charity, and Anna Mae Aquash
    - Crow Dog, Alex Bennett radio, "Weota Wicasha" / "Leonard on Creation" (audiocassette), undated; 1 (Box 118, Item barcode 39002091248949)
      Running time: 2 hours, 1 minute
      Summary: Mary Brave Bird describes personal events in her life, including her first menstruation and being raped as a young woman. She speaks about gender, violence, and sexuality. Another speaker, possibly Mary's sister, Barbara Moore, joins in and speaks about medicine men and their use of animals. Leonard talks about the legend of White Buffalo Woman, and about Creation. Mary discusses horses, and describes taking pills as a child and being hospitalized. Other topics include illness, dreams, and peyote